{"tossups": [{"question": "William Mead and this man were accused of \u201cspeaking in Gracechurch Street,\u201d but when the jury refused to a provide a guilty verdict, the judge starved the jury for two days before imprisoning them, too. This man wrote<em> No Cross, No Crown</em> while imprisoned in the Tower of London for allegedly denying the Trinity. In order to pay a debt to this man\u2019s father, Charles II made this man the largest non-royal landowner in the world. For ten points, name this Quaker who founded an American colony governed from Philadelphia.", "answer": "William<b> Penn</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As a teenager, this thinker built a calculator to aid his father\u2019s work as a tax supervisor. This man developed a law stating that a change in pressure at a point in a fluid is transmitted equally throughout the entire fluid. This man, who argued in support of Jansenism in<em> Provincial Letters</em>, names a diagram that conveniently displays the binomial coefficients; each value equals the sum of the two numbers above it in that \u201ctriangle.\u201d For ten points, name this 17th century French polymath.", "answer": "Blaise<b> Pascal</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "One response to this event was delayed when David Ige [ee-gay] forgot his Twitter password. This event, which took place during a shift-change operation, involved a failure to hear the words \u201cExercise, exercise, exercise,\u201d though it was originally blamed on a worker pressing the wrong button in a drop-down menu. The Emergency Alert System declared \u201cTHIS IS NOT A DRILL\u201d during, for ten points, what January 13, 2018 event that caused a brief panic in Honolulu?", "answer": "2018<b> Hawaii</b> ballistic<b> missile</b> false<b> alarm</b> incident (accept descriptive answers that incorporate all three underlined ideas; prompt on answers with only one or two of the three underlined ideas; accept descriptions of a<b> nuclear</b> attack in place of ballistic missile; accept any place in Hawaii, including <b>Honolulu</b> before it is mentioned, in place of Hawaii)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was known as the \u201cfierce\u201d in his early years after murdering 99 of his 100 brothers. This man, who rose to power after tricking Sushima into a pit of hot coals, was traumatized by seeing the Daya river allegedly run red with blood in the Kalinga wars. This son of Bindusara erected a rock edict at Sarnath detailing the importance of good deeds and adherence to Dharma. For ten points, name this Mauryan ruler who converted to Buddhism.", "answer": "<b> Ashok</b>a the Great (or<b> Asok</b>a the Great) Page 1", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "One work in this genre describes three generations of tribesmen led by Seitek, Semetei, and Manas. The demon Adamastor is battled by a group of sailors in one of these pieces of literature that tells of Vasco de Gama\u2019s voyage to India. Elias Lonrot compiled one of these works of literature from oral tradition, including the story of the creation of the Sampo. The<em> Lusiads</em> and the<em> Kalevala</em> are examples of, for ten points, what type of literature with a grand scope, such as the<em> Odyssey</em>?", "answer": "<b> epic</b> poems (accept national<b> epic</b>s; prompt on poems)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Prior to this event, covering fire from David Conner\u2019s Home Squadron allowed a commander to land his forces uncontested on Collado [co-yah-doh] Beach. Fighting centered around the fort of San Juan de Ul\u00b4ua during this event, which eventually forced the surrender of Juan Morales. After the battles of Monterrey and Buena Vista, Zachary Taylor\u2019s forces were given to Winfield Scott in preparation for this campaign. For ten points, name this 1847 event that led to the capture of a key Mexican seaport.", "answer": "Siege of<b> Veracruz</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One artist from this country showed the key to city of Breda being surrendered to a general of this country\u2019s army. In another work, the same artist included a self-portrait next to the reflection of this country\u2019s King Phillip IV in a mirror. Another painter active in this country was born in Crete and painted a landscape showing a \u201cView of\u201d of this country\u2019s city of Toledo [toh-LAY-doh]. For ten points, name this Iberian country home to the artist of<em> Las Meninas</em>, Diego Velazquez.", "answer": "<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man wrote that Catholicism and Marxism were incompatible, as Marxism has been used as a weapon to disobey the Christian faith. David Yallop speculated that this man was poisoned to prevent further investigation of Paul Marcinkus and Roberto Calvi. This man\u2019s death caused the most recent Year of Three Popes, as he was only in office for just over a month. For ten points, name this Pope who was succeeded in 1978 by Karol Wojtyla [voy-twah], a Polish cardinal whose papal name honored this man.", "answer": "<b> John Paul I</b> (or Albino<b> Luciani</b>; prompt on John Paul; do not prompt on John or Paul alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician introduced a bill to reduce infant mortality that initially did not reach the floor, but inspired the creation of the Sheppard-Towner Act in the next Congress. After losing a Republican primary to Oscar Lanstrum, this politician ran with the National Party but finished third behind Lanstrum and Thomas Walsh. This politician reasoned \u201cI can\u2019t go to war, and I refuse to send anyone else\u201d when she became the sole vote against declaring war on Japan. For ten points, name this Montana politician, the first female member of Congress.", "answer": "Jeannette<b> Rankin</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man resigned his rank of colonel after he was compared to Clement Vallandigham for a speech in which he blamed the British, Jews, and the presidency for pushing towards war. This man became the first ever<em> Time</em> Man of the Year after successfully completing a trip to Le Bourget that earned him the Orteig prize. The<em> Spirit of St. Louis</em> was flown by, for ten points, what American pilot who completed the first solo transatlantic flight?", "answer": "Charles<b> Lindbergh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer quoted the \u201cHabanera\u201d from Bizet\u2019s [bee-zay\u2019s]<em> Carmen</em> in the opening movement of a symphony whose finale was described as a \u201cparody of shrillness\u201d in the spurious autobiography<em> Testimony</em>. An opera by this composer focusing on Katerina Izmailova prompted Joseph Stalin to denounce him as\u201cformalist\u201d in the article \u201cMuddle Instead of Music.\u201d For ten points, what persecuted composer of<em> Lady</em> <em>Macbeth of the Mtsensk District</em> dubbed his Fifth Symphony \u201cA Soviet Artist\u2019s Reply to Just Criticism\u201dand wrote fifteen symphonies in total?", "answer": "Dmitri<b> Shostakovich</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, security guard Harald Jager [yay-ger] became a hero after refusing to stop a stampeding crowd. Tensions in this city were heightened as the result of a barricade erected in Operation Rose, culminating in a tank stand off near this city\u2019s Checkpoint Charlie. During Ronald Reagan\u2019s visit to this city, a request to \u201copen this gate\u201d was issued to Mikhail Gorbachev, along with a challenge to \u201ctear down this wall.\u201d For ten points, name this German city that was divided into east and west during the Cold War.", "answer": "<b> Berlin</b> (accept East and/or West<b> Berlin</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man accidentally sunk John Tyler\u2019s attempts to annex Texas after a letter to Richard Pakenham hoping for the expansion of slavery was exposed. While serving as James Monroe\u2019s Secretary for War, this man successfully set up the Bureau of Indian Affairs. This man penned an \u201cExposition and Protest\u201dcondemning the Tariff of Abominations, arguing that states should have a right to nullify federal laws. For ten points, name this member of the Great Triumvirate from South Carolina.", "answer": "John C.<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire was plunged into a series of civil wars after the assassinations of Berdibek and Janibeg, and it was dissolved after Akhmat backed down against troops from former vassal kingdoms at a standoff at the Ugra River. This empire\u2019s power diminished after Dmitri Donskoy liberated Moscow at the Battle of Kulikovo. The cities of Old and New Sarai were capitals of, for ten points, what kingdom that stretched into Western Europe, a Mongol horde named for the color of its tents?", "answer": "<b> Golden Horde</b> (accept<b> Kipchak</b> Khanate; prompt on Mongols before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, citizens defended themselves by removing guns from the ship<em> Aurora</em> and mounting them atop the Pulkovo Heights. Operation Northern Light brought the Gustav rail gun from the Crimea to this battle. Defenders in this battle were resupplied via the \u201cRoad of Life,\u201d where supplies were transported across the frozen Lake Ladoga. In 1941, Army Group North began, for ten points, what 900-day siege of a Russian city in World War II?", "answer": "Siege of<b> Leningrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A series of racially tinged riots in this city was triggered by Jos\u00b4e Diaz\u2019s death, the Sleepy Lagoon murder. Modern Pentecostalism was developed at this city\u2019s Foursquare Church</b> <b>by Aimee (+)</b> <b>Semple MacPherson, a decade after the end of the Azusa Street Revival in</b> <b>this city. This city\u2019s other race riots included a response to an attack on a motorist in its district of (*) </b> Watts, as well as a response to the beating of Rodney King. For ten points, name this large California city currently led by Mayor Eric Garcetti.", "answer": "<b> L</b>os<b> A</b>ngeles", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man employed James Alexander, who was quickly found in contempt; Andrew Hamilton and William Smith then defended him. This man, upset over the promotion of</b> <b>James DeLancey to replace Lewis (+)</b> <b>Morris, was condemned for his \u201cscandalous [...] and</b> <b>seditious reflections\u201d by William Cosby; this man\u2019s supporters noted, though, that (*)</b> truth is a defense against charges of libel. For ten points, name this German-American editor whose 1735 trial became a landmark defense of freedom of the press.", "answer": "John Peter<b> Zenger</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This nation\u2019s diplomats were forced to attend a peace conference held atop barges after they suffered defeats at the Battles of Eylau and Friedland. After violating the subsequent</b> <b>treaty, this nation used the (+)</b> <b>Unicorn artillery piece, the Bagration Fleches, and the</b> <b>Raevsky redoubt to defend its home soil at (*)</b> Borodino. Because this nation refused to follow the Treaty of Tilsit and join the Continental System against Britain, it was invaded in 1812. A harsh winter helped thwart Napoleon\u2019s invasion of, for ten points, what country led by Tsar Alexander I?", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>n Empire Page 9", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>These people were suppressed in one country after Antoine de La Valette went bankrupt on land deals in the Caribbean. These people upset the Marquis of Pombal by defending</b> <b>so-called \u201cReductions\u201d that housed Guarani natives in (+)</b> <b>South America. Clement XIV</b> <b>refused to meet with a leader of this group, Lorenzo Ricci, and ultimately suppressed them in 1773. The Tavora Affair ended with the (*) </b> expulsion of these people from Portugal, making teaching of the<em> Spirtiual Exercises</em> illegal. For ten points, name this powerful missionary order that was founded by Ignatius of Loyola.", "answer": "<b> Jesuit</b>s (accept members of the<b> Society of Jesus</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this city, Fort Independence stands at the site of Castle Williams, which once housed governor Thomas Hutchinson after an angry mob broke into his home. A declaration that</b> <b>\u201cthis (+)</b> <b>meeting can do nothing further to save the country\u201d was given at this city\u2019s</b> <b>Old South Meeting House, beginning an insurrection. This city\u2019s (*)</b> harbor was closed in the Coercive Acts after people dressed as Mohawks smashed crates of Darjeeling aboard ships. For ten points, name this city whose harbor was the site of an infamous 1773 tea party.", "answer": "<b> Boston</b> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man worked with his son-in-law Henry Ireton to win the Confederate Wars</b> <b>and conquer Ireland, a campaign that featured this man infamously sacking the town</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Drogheda when it refused to surrender. With Thomas Fairfax, this man</b> <b>masterminded a great victory at (*)</b> Naseby while commanding the New Model Army into battle against the Cavalier faction of loyalists that supported Charles I. For ten points, name this man who was named Lord Protector of England after the English Civil War.", "answer": "Oliver<b> Cromwell</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}